Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the
body of evidence
that links pesticides to
serious health problems.
And we start with an episode guest
hosted by Dr. Kristine Dennis,
our new Senior Research Scientist,
who has been researching and
scripting new video topics.
In this video, Kristine delves into
the association of vegetarian diets
and hypospadias birth defects
to see if it holds up in
the light of new research.
In 2000, a study found that a
vegetarian diet during pregnancy
was associated with hypospadias,
a specific birth defect
of the penis.
The authors suggested
that it may be due
to the greater exposure
to phytoestrogens,
which are found in soy foods.
But if you look globally,
while there is
an extraordinarily
high prevalence
in North America and Europe,
it's extremely low
in a country like Japan,
which has the highest per capita
soy intake in the world.
In fact, in Japan,
a low maternal intake
of soy phytoestrogens
has been associated with
elevated risk of hypospadias,
so, if anything,
soy may be protective.
If soy foods aren't
the hormone disrupters,
what in a vegetarian diet
might be?
Well, occupational
exposure to pesticides
is associated with higher risk,
so, might low-level pesticide
exposure among those eating
more fruits and vegetables--
like vegetarians--
help explain it?
If you randomize people
to a more plant-based
Mediterranean diet,
you see a large increase
in the amount of pesticides
flowing through their body,
though, of course,
if you put them
on a Mediterranean diet
with organic fruits
and vegetables,
you see a 90 percent drop
in pesticide exposure.
So, does organic food
consumption during pregnancy
reduce hypospadias risk?
Apparently so,
cutting the odds about in half,
particularly when
it comes to choosing
organic vegetables and dairy,
though the only other study
to look at organic food choices
and hypospadias
found the risk associated
just with conventional
high-fat dairy products.
It isn't all or nothing.
Even if only two thirds
of your produce is organic,
that can significantly reduce
pesticide exposure,
but the benefits of consuming
conventionally grown produce
likely outweigh any possible
risks from pesticide exposure,
so, concerns over
ingesting pesticides
should never discourage
fruit and vegetable intake.
In the United States alone,
if you add up all
of the fatal cancers, strokes,
heart attacks, and other deaths
that could have been averted
simply by eating
more fruits and vegetables,
it comes out to nearly
450,000 deaths every year.
That's how powerful
produce can be.
But might one of the downsides
be this hypospadias risk?
Despite their high
plant consumption,
vegetarians may be less exposed
to conventional pesticides,
but that's because
of their greater propensity
to choose organic produce.
Now, the researchers only
considered the pesticides
in plant foods,
not animal products,
and even for
conventional insecticides,
animal products are
main contributors to exposure.
Additionally,
persistent pesticides,
such as organochlorine
pesticides like DDT,
are concentrated in fish,
other meats, and dairy,
so it's no surprise
that the blood of
strictly plant-based eaters
ends up significantly
less polluted.
It may not just be from the
lower level of intake, though;
high fiber diets can bulk up the
stool and glom on to pesticides
and flush them away.
In the end, the hypospadias
issue may be another example
of the stroke scare.
Dr. Greger did a whole series
covering potential explanations
why a study had found higher
stroke rates among vegetarians,
but then, half a dozen
other studies found
lower rates of stroke,
if anything, across the board.
The original hypospadias study
looked at about 50 cases.
Twelve years later,
a study that looked
at 1,250 cases was published
and found zero increased risk
among vegetarian mothers.
In our next story,
researchers measure the
impact of eating organic
on the levels of
pesticides in our children.
Produce can be contaminated
by manure runoff,
and conventional produce may
be contaminated with pesticides.
We’ve known for years
that the 800 million pounds
of pesticides used annually
in the United States—
herbicides, fungicides, insecticides—
have clear-cut detrimental effects
on farm workers and their families.
That’s uncontroversial.
We can even do what are
called hand-wipe studies
to actually measure the pesticides
in the hands of kids in
California’s Central Valley.
The planes come down and spray this fog.
How much exposure urban and suburban
children are getting from food, however,
has been unclear,
until now.
Twice daily, urine samples were taken
from 3-to 11-year-olds
for more than a year
to see how much pesticide
is flowing through our kids.
These children were nowhere near
farms, or fog-spraying planes.
And to single out pesticides
that were coming from the diet,
as opposed to a lawn
treatment or something,
for two weeks of the year, the
kids were put on organic diet.
Guess which two weeks those were?
So the two times during the year
when they ate organic foods,
there were undetectable,
or nearly undetectable,
pesticide residues in their urine,
while their little bodies were basically
swimming in it the rest of the year.
In my 2000 update, I told everyone
about this disturbing study.
Vegetarianism during pregnancy
associated with having sons
with a specific birth defect of
the penis called hypospadias.
They thought it might have something
to do with the phytoestrogens in soy,
but that didn’t make
any sense since Japan,
with the highest per capita
soy consumption in the world,
did not have high rates of the defect.
I guessed that it might be low vitamin
B12 levels leading to high homocysteine,
which has been related
to other birth defects,
but we were all wrong.
Finally, though, the mystery
seems to have been solved.
The researchers reanalyzed the data
for clues as to what could be found
in the diets of vegetarians
compared to meat eaters—
other than more good things,
like more fruits and vegetables.
Unless, there is an endocrine-disrupting
fungicide, called vinclozolin,
that is sprayed on most
of our conventional crops,
which we now know causes hypospadias.
So, researchers went back and split up
the vegetarian moms into two groups:
those eating organic produce, and
those eating conventional produce.
And while the vegetarian women
eating conventional produce
during pregnancy had indeed
higher birth defects rates,
there was not a single
case in the organic group.
So it seems the hypospadias
wasn’t due to vegetarian diets;
it was that they were exposing
their fetus to more pesticides.
Can’t we just rinse our produce off?
Well, it’s better than nothing,
but this new study looked at
three pesticides on apples.
Levels start out at 100%.
Rinsing seems to take off only
about 15% of the pesticides.
The only way to really cut down
our dose is to peel the apple,
eliminating about 85% of the pesticides—
but also eliminating
much of the nutrition.
So, eat organic foods whenever possible.
Organic produce has more
vitamins, more minerals,
tastes better, stores better,
and you get to not be complicit in the
poisoning farm workers and their families.
Finally today,
how can we avoid the
breakdown product of pesticides
that may increase the risk
of Alzheimer’s disease?
Although there is a growing list
of Alzheimer's disease
susceptibility genes, even if
you put them all altogether,
they account for less than half
of all Alzheimer's cases.
The single most compelling piece
of data on the potential control
we have over the disease
is the fact that if you have
identical twins, with the exact
same genes, even if one gets
Alzheimer's the other
usually does not.
So, we have to think
about all the other
contributing factors
beyond just genetics.
In my video on pesticides and cancer,
I talked about this study.
There’s a list of chlorinated
pesticides, including DDE
(a metabolite of DDT) that
are classified by the EPA
as probable human carcinogens.
But in the study, blood
levels of DDE and others were
associated not with
increased cancer mortality,
but increased risk of
other-cause mortality.
This led researchers to
speculate it may be due to
an associated increased risk
of diabetes or dementia.
I’ve talked previously
about the diabetes link.
What about dementia?
“Elevated Serum Pesticide Levels
and Risk for Alzheimer Disease.”
A research team at Rutgers found
significantly higher blood
levels of DDE in Alzheimer’s disease
patients compared to controls,
and autopsy studies
show blood levels
are a good proxy for brain levels.
Those with the highest levels
were at about four times
the odds of being
demented with Alzheimer's.
And in a petri dish, DDE increases
amyloid precursor protein levels
in human brain cells, providing
a potential mechanism.
Put all these studies together,
and there does indeed seem
to be a link, consistent with
data showing about a doubling
of risk for developing dementia among
those acutely pesticide poisoned.
Among U.S. elders, DDT and its
breakdown product DDE are also
associated with increased risk
of cognitive decline in general.
DDT was extensively
used in the United States
from the 1940s through the 1960s.
At its peak, we were churning
out 180 million pounds a year.
And it’s still in our bodies to this day,
contaminating the bloodstreams of
more than 90 percent of Americans,
and DDE, the pesticide
linked to quadrupling the odds
of Alzheimer’s, were at the highest levels.
It’s still in our bodies because
it’s still in the food supply.
In my last video on the topic,
I noted that the levels of
DDT, DDE, and other banned
pesticides and pollutants
were much lower in the breast
milk from a vegetarian mother
compared to breast milk of
her non-vegetarian sister.
And the largest difference
was noted for DDE,
which was four times lower
in the vegetarian sister.
This is what you see across the
board for these kinds of pollutants.
Food samples were collected from
supermarkets across the U.S.
Here’s what they found
for dioxins and PCBs
in beef, chicken, pork,
processed meat, eggs, fish,
all plant-foods put together,
and dairy products.
These toxins build up the food
chain; so, it makes sense that
the most contaminated foods are
meat, fish, and dairy products.
5 to 10 times higher
levels in meat, eggs,
fish, and dairy than what
they found in plant foods.
And unfortunately, cooking doesn’t
destroy pollutants like DDE—
in fact it may make them
even more concentrated.
And this is for a pesticide
that may increase the risk
of Alzheimer’s disease as
much as if you carried
the so-called Alzheimer’s
gene APOE4.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.